Finding Aid for Luce Philippine Project interviews, 1975-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Luce Philippine Project interviews 1975-1980
University of Michigan. Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies.
2 linear feet including 107 audiocassettes
8772 Bimu C539 2
Oral history interviews collected as part of a project of the University of Michigan Center for South and Southeast Asia Studies, funded by the Henry Luce Foundation, on "U.S.-Philippine Interactions as Reflected in Oral Histories."
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in multiple accessions, from the Luce Philippine Project through Mike Cullinane (donor no. 6337 ) in 1979, from Morton and Petra Netzorg (donor no. 6982 ) in 1987, and the University of Michigan Library through Susan Go in 2014.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research. Within each series, the researcher should note that not all of the interviewees signed release forms permitting the transfer of their interviews to the University of Michigan.
In 1977 the University of Michigan Center for South and Southeast Asia Studies received support from the Henry Luce Foundation for a three-year project on "U.S.-Philippine Interactions as Reflected in Oral Histories." One part of the grant-funded project was to provide monies to Michigan faculty and students undertaking oral history, both in the Philippines and among Filipinos and Americans with Philippine experience (former diplomats, teachers, missionaries, servicemen, colonial officials, etc.) in the United States. As a result of this project, the Bentley Historical Library received tapes from two researchers, Michael Cullinane, at that time research associate in the Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies and later associate director of the Center for Southeast Asian Studies of University of Wisconsin--Madison, and Petra Fuld Netzorg, manager of the Cellar Book Shop in Detroit, Michigan, which specialized in Philippine publications.
The collection contains four series of oral history interviews, all recorded on audiocassettes. The series are: Forrest McGill, Petra Fuld Netzorg, Michael P. Onorato, and Bienvenido Santos.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Philippines--History--1946-1986.; United States--Relations--Philippines.; Philippines--Relations--United States.
Contributors
Agasid, Napoleon.; Amper, Arcadio.; Andaya, Herman.; Araneta, Salvador.; Bareng, T.; Bowler, Mary Summers.; Boyarski, Dick.; Cagas, Antonio.; Cagas, Filomena.; Carter, Thomas M.; Edades, Jean G.; Edades, Victorio C., 1895-; Felipe, F.; Foronda, S.; Gastillo, Hugo.; Hester, Evett D.; Hornbostel, Earl, 1915-2001.; Hufana, Alejandrino G.; José, F. Sionel (Francisco Sionel), 1924-; Laudico, Yolande.; Leon, Felipe M.; Lucas, Mae Whitacre.; Madarang, Felipe.; Manning, John L.; Martin, Charlotte Hagans.; McGill, Forrest, 1947-; Medico, P.; Nagal, A.; Netzorg, Petra Fuld.; Ogatis, C.; Onorato, Michael Paul, 1934-; Paras-Perez, Rodolfo.; Reyes, Linda.; Rivera, R.; Santos, Beinvenido N.; Segura, Manuel F.; Stewart, Gertrude Hornbostel, 1918-1992.; Tampon, Casimera.; Torres, Emmanuel.; Tumaeder, Candido.; Urbistondo, Macario.; Henry Luce Foundation.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Sound recordings.
- Forrest McGill series
  Forrest McGill series: Four cassettes containing interviews conducted by Forrest McGill, who received his Ph.D. in Asian art history from the University of Michigan in 1977, later chief curator, Asian Art Museum, San Francisco. These interviews with members of the arts community were conducted in July 1978 in the Philippines. Transcripts are found in the collection.
  Researchers are warned that the interviewees did not sign release forms permitting the transfer of their interviews to the University of Michigan.
  - Audiocassettes
    - Cassette 1 Side A: F. Sionel José (novelist, gallery owner) July 18, 1978, Emmanuel (Eric) Torres (director, Ateneo Art Gallery), July 21, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Cassette 1 Side B: Dr. Rodolfo Paras-Perez (National Library artist and critic) July 20, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Cassette 2: Emmanuel Torres July 26, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Cassette 3 Side A: A. G. Hufana (novelist, painter, librarian of Cultural Center of the Philippines) July 11, 1978, Linda Reyes (painter, art instructor at University of the Philippines Manila), July 12, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Cassette 3 Side B: Linda Reyes continued; Yolande Laudico (painter, assistant director Museum of Philippine Art) July 13, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Cassette 4 Side A: Felipe de Leon, Jr. (chair, Humanities Dept., University of the Philippines) July 17, 1978 Yolande Laudico, July 18, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Cassette 4 Side B: Yolande Laudico continued; F. Sionel José July 18, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Transcripts, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Petra Fuld Netzorg series
  Petra Fuld Netzorg series: 27 cassettes containing interviews conducted by Petra Fuld Netzorg, manager of the Cellar Book Shop in Detroit, Michigan. The interviews were conducted in the Philippines between December 1979 and February 1980. The interviewees include long-time American residents of the Philippines, Philippine artists, and others. No transcripts are included, but the collection includes photographs and background information for most of the interviewees.
  John L. Manning, Charlotte Hagans Martin, and Manuel Segura signed release forms transferring their interviews to the University of Michigan. The library does not have releases for the other interviewees.
  - Audiocassettes
    - Mary Summers Bowler (Mrs. William Bowler, daughter of George Summers) January 24, 1980 Cebu City, 1 1/4 hours; 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Tom Carter (American President Lines agent in the Philippines) February 21, 1980, 2 hours; 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Jean and Victorio Edades (1895-1985 national artist) January 27-28, 1980 Davao City, 4 hours; 3 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Hugo Gastillo (sanitary inspector during colonial period) January 9, 1980 Libmanan, Camarines Sur, 1 hour; 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Dr. Evett D. Hester (economic advisor to commonwealth government, counselor for economic affairs in U.S. embassy) December 27, 1979 Manila at Army-Navy Club, 1 1/4 hours; 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Earl Hornbostel (1915-2001 internee at Santo Tomas during World War II) February 19, 1980, 8 1/2 hours; 7 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - John L. Manning (president Manila Trading and Supply Co., internee at Santo Tomas during World War II) December 27, 1979, 4 hours; 3 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Charlotte Hagans Martin and Mae Whitacre Lucas January 23, 1980 Cebu City, at the Bowlers, 1 1/2 hours; 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Charlotte Hagans Martin and Dick Boyarski February 3, 1980 Cebu City, 1 1/2 hours; 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
      (marked "Tape 2")
    - Col. Manuel F. Segura (Adjutant General of the Cebuano guerrillas during World War II) January 22, 1980 Cebu City, 2 1/2 hours; 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Gertrude Hornbostel Stewart (1918-1992 Manila businesswoman, sister of Earl Hornbostel, internee at Santo Tomas during World War II), January 6 and February 17, 1980, 7 hours; 5 audiocassettes (Box 1)
  - Papers
    - Mary Summers Bowler photographs, includes family photos (Box 1)
    - Tom Carter photographs and copies of published reminiscences (Box 1)
    - Jean and Victorio Edades photographs and copies of published reminiscences (Box 1)
    - Hugo Gastillo photographs, includes family photos (Box 1)
    - Dr. Evett D. Hester photographs and biographical information (Box 1)
    - Earl Hornbostel photographs and biographical information (Box 1)
    - John L. Manning photographs and biographical information, including family photos (Box 1)
    - Charlotte Hagans Martin photographs, includes photos of Mae Whitacre Lucas and Dick Boyarski (Box 1)
    - Col. Manuel F. Segura photograph (Box 1)
    - Gertrude Hornbostel Stewart photographs (Box 1)
- Michael P. Onorato series
  Michael P. Onorato series: Thirteen cassettes containing interviews of Philippine statesman Salvador Araneta conducted by Michael P. Onorato in June 1975 and March 1976. The interviews were conducted at Araneta's home in Vancouver, British Columbia. Onorato was a faculty member at California State University, Fullerton. An edited transcript is found in the collection
  Tapes may not be copied or transcribed without written consent of the Oral History Project, California State University, Fullerton. Citations to these interviews should read: "Araneta-Onorato Interview, 1975-1976. An Oral History Project of California State University, Fullerton."
  - Audiocassettes
    - Salvador Araneta interview June 1975, 11 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Salvador Araneta interview March 1976, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
  - Papers
    - Transcript, "Salvador Araneta: Reflections of a Filipino Exile" (Box 1)
- Bienvenido Santos series
  Bienvenido Santos series: One cassette containing an undated lecture by Philippine novelist Bienvenido Santos (1911-1996), entitled "American Influence on Filipino Literature."
  Santos did not sign a release form permitting the transfer of his lecture to the University of Michigan.
  - Audiocassettes
    - Lecture, "American Influence on Filipino Literature," undated (Box 1)
- Michael Cullinane
  Michael Cullinane series: 62 cassettes containing interviews of Philippine migrant workers in Hawaii conducted by Michael Cullinane in August-October 1979.
  None of the interviewees signed release forms permitting the transfer of their interviews to the University of Michigan.
  - Audiocassettes
    - Napoleon Agasid interviews August 16, 1979, 4 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - Arcadio Amper interviews September 10, 1979, 4 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - Herman Andaya interviews August 17, 1979, 3 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - T. Bareng interviews August 1, 1979, 3 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - Filomena and Antonio Cagas interviews October 2, 1979, 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - F. Felipe interviews August 24-26, 1979, 4 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      Cassettes are numbered 1-2, 4, 6
    - S. Foronda interviews September 9, 1979, September 16, 1979, 5 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      Cassettes are numbered 1, 3-6
    - Felipe Madarang interviews October 10, 1979, 4 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - P. Medico interviews August 27, 1979, 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - A. Nagal interviews August 31, 1979, 8 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - C. Ogatis interviews August 24, 1979, 4 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      Cassettes are numbered 3, 5-6, and one unnumbered
    - R. and V. Rivera interviews August 10, 1979, 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - Casimera Tampon interviews September 30, 1979, 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - Candido Tumaeder interviews August 16, 1979, 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - Macario Urbistondo interviews September 23, 1979, 7 audiocassettes (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, 6 audiocassettes (Box 2)